Hello community. So great that you are
back. Honestly, I just wanted to tell
you in a very short video, hey, we have
a new transformer. Yes, a absolute new
transformer architecture. Not the good
old transformer from Google that was
invented by Google and patented by
Google. But now we have Mus with memory
and it is available for you. Look,
hugging face. You have it here updated
two days ago. You have a 4B model. You
have a 9B model. It is there for you and
it is compatible here with the hugging
phase numitation. So you just go there
and this is the code. It is there
available for you using the classical
transformer code absolutely compatible.
You have a GitHub repo for you, an
English Chinese paper overview, quick
start, training, evaluation, citation,
everything for you. And you have a
beautiful paper, a mathematical, I mean
a a computer science paper here on the
new ME tensor algebra. And you might
say, why is nobody talking about it?
Look, it was published on July 29, 2026.
And I have to say, this is a new
transformer model. This is a new memory
foundation model that is absolutely
interesting because it stands close to
the classical transformer model because
you know we only have a transformer
model and then we have some diffusion
models and then we have some mumba malls
but more or less all our important
models are transformer-based model and
now we have a new one. So gee this is
interesting but look at this. Okay, the
main orchard is here from a Shanghai
Technology Corporation, a spin-off here.
But look, he's also here a member of the
Renman University of China and we have
from the National University of
Singapore, the Shanghai Geotong
University, the Tongi University. So, it
seems to me this is here a classical
university spin-off. So, I'm absolutely
pro startup companies that take some
insights from the university studies and
they they start a classical startup.
Now, so let's have a look.
You know what's nice? You can say forget
something. You can say, "Hey, please
forget that Alice likes to eat beef
burger." And then when you come back and
says, "Hey, what does Alice like to
eat?" And the Yan comes back and says,
"Hey, I don't have that information." Do
you know how complex our current
procedure is to delete memories from my
eye system?
Now I looked at the paper and I said
what is here the cause that people are
not reading the paper and are not
fascinated here by the inside of this
paper. I mean just look at it. So I had
three questions. Why is everybody
ignoring this beautiful new preprint?
I mean just think about this new forget
technology that is suddenly available
for everybody. You can download from
hugging face. And gee, we have a new
transformer architecture with a new
complexity regarding memory that we had
to put in a hornness or into a rack
system. I mean, come on.
They have such a beautiful additional
explanation about everything. They even
have a theoretical error analysis. They
have here a classical tailor expansion.
They really want to know, hey, how
sensible is our result here? How far can
we go and tell here our community? Yeah,
this is actually working. So, let's have
a look at this. And I tried to make it
within 5 minutes, but maybe I need a
little bit more. So, I think Matis is a
first prototype. It's a prototype of a
new what they call a memory foundation
model. So, it is an LLM, but it builds
upon the Google Transformer architecture
and it integrates memory in new unseen
ways. Remember
all other people on this planet use
external memory modules. No classical
agent may appear to have memory but the
backbone itself does not. The database
stores the past event and embedding
model indexes them. The retriever
selects no particular passages. The
reranker filters them again. The
selected text is concatenated to a
particular prompt structure and then the
lm processes this particular prompt
structure again. So this means the agent
is stateful only because the surrounding
harness repeatedly reconstructed to
state for the LLM of a core of an agent.
So we do have if you want an
architectural decoupling from the core
LLM and intelligent of the harness where
the harness is actually preparing here
the state for the LLM and preparing here
the prompt structure and we do have
problems with this external memory. We
have a target mismatch. External rack
system fetched the text based on surface
level embeddings while the ALM backbone
might actually need deeper latent
representation from its own core that
are not identical with a vector database
representation. We do have an
optimization bottleneck. You cannot back
propagate gradients efficiently through
a discrete non-ifferiable external
database operation. And of course, our
key value cache will just explode. And
yeah
and there's also a deeper memory
paradox. No at storage time the system
does not yet know what particular future
question the memory or the information
or the facts or the knowledge the
procedural knowledge should be encoded.
So therefore memory is fundamentally if
you think about it uh from an abstract
point of view a predictive compression
problem. Think about a vector space.
This is just a a compressed
representation of some data. So we do
have a present information level but we
need a compressed state that anticipates
here more or less the future use. So we
can encode it in an optimal
representation that whenever the
question comes in let's say about the
physics or medicine or finance that we
do have an optimal presentation for this
particular use case.
And this new preprint the central
proposal is more or less that a
compression policy should be learned
jointly with the way the m the new
transformer will later read and have
access to the memory. A career in
structure.
So let's take a step back. Mis now as we
call this new methodology replaces what
we have as a discrete rack workflow with
a continuous function space that is
natively integrated into the
transformer.
Finally after almost 10 years the
transformer architecture patented by
Google is now further developed. Yes,
beautifully. So they introduce here what
they call here not a transformer block
but a mis block in the transformer block
and they have two different block
structures. So they have a local memory
block that is representing the current
memory state and this block is updated
by a static trainable hypermemory block
that is based on the current context
complexity.
Or if you want to have it simplified and
if you have seen this video where I show
this low and fast training of the eye,
slow for the eye weights and fast for
the eye harness, you know this level one
and level two syncing. You can see it
also in this framing. The hyperblock
contains the trained slow weights and
the local block contains the runtime
fast weights.
So this is our classical architecture
here. External decoupling with the
information the external blocked
gradient and we have some sequential
output structure. And now comes the new
idea. The aortes now hypothesize that
just as reasoning here in the last two
years became a native capability of our
models. Remember it all started with
chain of sword. Now memory is the next
object we should bring into the
transformer and not leave in the
harness. So memory should also be
internalized directly into the forward
pulse computation in the layers of a
transformer architecture as a set of
dynamic persistent parameters
and the authors did a beautiful job. I
just want to show you here their
explanation of our good old transformer
our friend for the last 10 years. The
causal language model we denote a
sequence of input tokens. Causal
language model first maps the discrete
tokens into a continuous vector
representation. Let E denote the token
embedding matrix where V is the
vocabulary size. The initial hidden
state is obtained extracting the
corresponding embedding and combining
them with the positional rope
embeddings. And after that the initial
representation is processed sequently
through the stack of end transformer
block by our hidden layers. And then the
final hidden state represents the
contextualized input and the language
model head maps this final state back to
the vocabulary space to predict the pro
the probability distribution for the
next token. This process is commonly
mold by linear projection of the
normalization followed by a classical
softmax function and here h is the final
hidden vector the position and w
represents the projection matrix down.
After sampling, this new token is
appended to the sequence and the model
repeats the process until it decodes an
end of sequence token reaches its
maximum length. Beautiful to the point
absolute gorgeous description of the
transformer in a functional density that
is just yeah that's it. And they explain
pre-training. Yes, of course. Standard
auto reggressive next token prediction
objective. This is it. So now let's have
a look understanding now of the
classical architecture.
They now alter the causal self attention
mechanism defining now some specific
native memory storage and some memory
utilization procedures and they are more
or less three steps in my wording and I
make it a little bit simpler because if
you want to read the paper go it's a
little bit on the mathematical side. I
just want to give you the main idea. So
we do have a native memory state. So
instead of a growing key value cache in
a classical self attention historical
knowledge now after interaction with the
CI system is compressed compactified
into and now this is here just an
approximation but the order a fixed size
dense memory matrix M and a key
normalization vector at each layer time
step T. Okay.
So the native storage procedure so we
write now this now to decide what to
remember the hypermemory block learns an
importance vector W to score the current
hidden state. So this is here a
self-learned mechanism where this CI
system is now trained to identify here
or assign an importance factor given a
particular piece of information of data
streams here and you can score this. So
you have then a top down top 20 down
most important vector states and hidden
states and then you have the read
procedure know you have the native
utilization procedure you read out this
memory and the beauty is now you don't
have to go with some complex
mathematical you just do this during the
forward pass metas queries here this
internal memory state using here learned
memory query projection so we're real
close to the original self attention
mechanism and the standard attention
output is simply now mixed mixed I show
you the formula in a minute with the
memory attention readout using here a
kind of a balancing parameter gamma this
is it so instead of a growing key value
cache we have here if you want the right
and the read procedure and all of this
is done here coh in a coherent
mathematical apparatus so that we can
mix it with the standard self attention
mechanisms
Great. So yeah, this is our attention
mechanism. So we have the original
attention and then we have here our new
terms and of course we have to train
this now. So they call it here they call
this here a mid training because here
they want to train it here on some
synthetic data to explicitly learn the
operation via some loss objective. And
[snorts] they came up with the idea okay
we do have multiple elements of this
loss function. We have a reconstruction
loss. We have exactly this update for
get to reflect loss function and then
kind of a regularization prevent the
hallucination and the pollution loss
function.
So now you see see our architecture
changed our optimization procedure
changed and the efficiency increased
significantly.
Great. Now that we have a feeling what
is expected here and what the orers had
in mind. Let's have now a closer look.
As I told you, they say in our
transformer layer, we add now a mus
block and a mus block inside the
transformer block here of the Google
transformer has a local memory block and
a hypermemory block. Beautiful.
The local memory block as you see is
adapted at the testing phase and the
hypermemory block is optimized at the
training phase. So you understand
immediately thinking back to the rag
optimized procedures. Okay, I understand
what the local memory block are
responsible for maintaining the dense
representation of the prior information
while the hyper memory block constructs
of course a parametric function space
for native memory procedures to
transform here the memory state. This is
also what we have done here with hyperx
systems.
Now if you say hm why do we have a local
memory block and a hyper memory block
just look here in one of my last videos
we had the same no we were talking here
about a multi- aent topology
optimization during the inference run
and I told you here if you take this
controller step here for the repair of
the optimized if you want trace back
topology then I just said hey look this
short-term playbook just understand it
as a short-term memory memory
optimization and here the reflector
after I think 24 steps or 12 steps here
now rewrites now what have I learned
this is just here if you want a
long-term memory or a particular skill
update that you transfer into a new
skill and you can update this skill so
the idea of a short-term memory of a
long-term memory just in we encountered
here in one of my last videos so this
idea is nothing new it is just how they
implemented it not in a playbook like
here for the topology
in a verbal description but now we go
deep into the transformer architecture
and we build it here in the mathematical
understanding of the transformer.
So the local memory block maintains a
memory state at the current step we
define a dense memory network M. This is
our matrix representation inside the ELF
local memory block. So at a particular
step T, we denote it as M depending on T
and the model also maintains a query key
normalization vector. This is important.
This is S. So we have M and S. And both
M and S are dynamic parameters updated
across different steps. At the first
when we start, we have everything down
at zero. And then we go. Now the
hypermemory block are responsible for
updating here the dynamic parameters in
our local memory block based here on the
intermediate activation absolutely of
the current input X and the output Y. So
each of them consists of a static
parameter obtained to mid training which
remain unchanged during the interaction
parametric foundation. Yes blah blah
blah you're familiar with this. So this
means we have well we start here with a
learned importance vector that scores
every single token and then the system
selects the smallest number of the
highest scoring token. So what is the
most important content of my data stream
whose accumulative probability reaches
here or crosses over a particular
threshold. So the system identifies hey
this is a new information. This is an
information I need here given my
parametric knowledge and my learned
capabilities. This is something I have
to remember. And this selective
aggregation here of probabilities of
course is if you want experimentally the
most important architectural component
here in this hypermemory block
and what we do we go the classical way
of a transformer. We build here
construct memory keys and memory values.
And remember in the classical self
attention and cross attention we had the
same we had here our textual keys and
our textual value composition. And now
we do this for the memory structures. So
the selected hidden states are projected
into a learned memory space. So we just
build if you want in the simplest case
we just add a new mathematical space
where we put the most important memory
elements of our discussion that I had
with my EI of the last two months. So
what really happened in this two months?
And then of course we have to find a
mathematical representation. So we
compress this into a tensor structure
into a matrix structure. So we convert
here a variable number of tokens and
with the probability and the relation
and whatever into now they or go
interestingly with a fixed size
associative memory matrix.
Now this is interesting. This has some
implications, no because we do have
temporal decay because I'm constantly
talking to my eye. So the memory matrix
will fill up with newer, more important
information. So this means we do have a
temporal decay since it's fixed size. So
something has to fall out at the other
end of the matrix this old unimportant
stuff that has already been updated.
Yeah.
And then what we just have to do then we
just have to fuse it here with the
ordinary intent attention. So matis now
retains the standard causal attention
mechanism that you know and combines it
simply with the memory attention
mechanism that looks quite similar. Now
this is our current attention. This is
our new memory attention. And then the
transformer receives two information
streams.
the current interaction and the memory
if you want the compressed history data
and the memory is injected as a residual
source at multiple transformer depths
rather than a text here at the input
where we start with our embedding and
rope and position encoding. So this is
now a deep layer mathematical operation
in the transformer where we just combine
or simply add here the memory attention
in a very particular way and gamma is
our factor here.
If you want to see this here in a flow
diagram, beautiful. This is exactly what
we just went through. This is our native
storage procedure with our misus block
that is part here of our transformer
block. Now you see we have here in green
the original attention. You see this
here I follow here the shade and then
then comes the interesting step. Now we
have here the [clears throat] memory
attention that is calculated. We just
went through this and you might say,
"Hey, do we have a little bit more of a
mathematical details?" Oh, I'm so glad
you asked because this is it here. Now,
we already went through this. This was
the native memory utilization procedure.
Huh? But now we go a little bit deeper
into the mathematics. So, we define now
the memory attention in a complete way.
This is it a gilder. This is for matrix.
Yeah, this is a diagonal element. have
the details in the paper where our Q
denotes the memory query states with
optimizable parameter. We add an
identity vector to the normalization
denominator to prevent the numerical
overflow improve numerical stability.
And then the memory attention is
integrated into the main branch of the
tension and replaces our first equation
with this particular equation where the
norm is applied to the memory readout
also to align the scale with the
original attention branches and
everything is according to what we
already know from a classical transform
architecture.
After completing this we denote that the
input hidden state at the out layer is
here our hidden layer L minus one. Then
the hypermemory block aggregates this
into a compact representation. So we
learned adaptive aggregation. Here's the
softmax formula that you are familiar
with at a particular uh temperature
here. And then everything is expressed
with L that we know and denotes here the
minimum number and the dense memory
network is updated here. This is our M
and this is our S parameter that we
talked already at the beginning of this
video. And here you have it now in
mathematical beauty.
So what does it mean after all of this?
Let's take a step back. So up until last
week before this paper was published two
days ago, what was memory? Memory was
simple. No, memory in our models was
either a textual memory or it was a
latent memory in a mathematical vector
space for example or it was part here of
the learned experiences of the LLM and
it was part of the parametric memory of
the core of the agent the LLM or VLM
itself.
Now we have a new mechanism number four
arrived.
Just as a sum up textual memory
typically represents information as text
relying here on rag retrieval augmented
generation for storage and retrieval.
The methods provide information for
backbone to support inference by in
context learning our good old friend
ICL. You have an example here memory
tree or memory bank whatever you build
it. Latent memory captures the memory
through intermediate activations of the
model. Next mem genen our typical models
and then we had parametric knowledge
memory and parametric memory injects
here the knowledge into the internal
model parameters. This is here really
our tensor weights. No. Yeah. Rome for
example. Beautiful. So you see the
storage mechanism was either a classical
rack or the LM weight modification with
complete fine-tuning
with rack we had what it is stored words
and records how it is written the
harness for rack writes here the text
and then the harness decide how to bring
it together and present it then to the
LLM how it is retrieved retrieve text
and insert into the prompt for the core
LLM with the weight it was different
yeah we had a gradient based training
and was automatically activated during
the inference run and now we have mis
state. So what is now stored a
compressed latent association from
recent interaction what we call memory.
How is it written? It is written as a
forward pass fast weight update. So
completely different to the harness or
the gradientbased training. This is not
just a forward pass update. And how is
it retrieved? It is an internal memory
attention branch of the complete self
attention mechanism, cross attention
mechanism, multi head self attention
mechanism of a classical Google
transform architecture.
What is now why why we need it? What is
different? So mi's intended role is now
to be rapidly writable,
internally accessible within the
transformer and a latent experience. So
we don't have to transform it back to
English words and we can stay within the
mathematical optimized spaces.
Yeah. Then you auto show us hey we we
learned this. No we trained mus the
training included 357,000 primary
samples 46 million primary data tokens
27 sources and benchmarks 600,000
samples and beautiful great they did all
of this and we absolutely trust them.
Gorgeous. So we have a Chinese startup
or Singapore startup
insights. Let's look at the result. The
overall performance are memory based Q&R
tasks. No. And they go here with two
different benchmarks. Locomo and here
next ma'am. Beautiful. Now let's look at
here what I showed you the QN 3.5 27
billion model. This is if you want the
pure QN3. And then based on the Q1 3.5
they added this particular training for
Amitis and we go here also for the 27
billion free trainable parameter model.
Now just look at here the performance
average here we have 0.07
from a Q1 on this particular benchmark.
So this is almost nothing but look at
Mis 27B. Here we have 26.74
compared to 0.07.
The other benchmark here locom or next
mam here also average we have here 17
for the pure cuban 3.5 27b and for our
matis 27b we have now 50.82.
So you might say okay this is absolutely
impressive. So for this particular test
for this particular complexity this new
memory inner transformer is really a
performance jump. But wait a minute,
wait a minute. We have to read the paper
real carefully and maybe activate a
little bit our human brain to understand
what's happening because look at this.
This is now here the Cuban 3.527B
with the full context given. So if mis
does not have to do anything with its
memory you provide everything at the
data the information the factual data
the procedural data full context given
to the Q13.5 27B and now this mall has a
performance here instead of 26 now we
have 65 and go to the next M benchmark
instead of here average 50.82 we have
now a performance of 78.8 date. So this
means okay so whatever mat is decided to
encode as important memory knowledge
that it should keep given or expecting a
particular complexity level as a query
my human query it is not there yet if
you give the system absolute continuous
full access to all the necessary data
but compared to an average of 0.07% 07%
I would say okay it is a significant
jump forward but I would argue here that
the mis the mis native memory selection
there's space that we can further
optimize it no because it is really not
as good as you provide the cub with the
complete textual evidence.
Yeah, but compared here to no context
evaluation, it just performs here all
the other ones.
What is really interesting, but also we
will see later limitation. Mus
completely avoids a delinear grow of the
key value caching and our classical
transformer at they have here context
window of 128k. matrix requires
practically constant storage only 2 MB
of lowering approximation and say hey
wait a minute lowerang approximation
yeah this is a trick that they used
compared to the full context standard
here okay so but this has implication
now look at this here we have here let's
go for this solid line m's first step is
here in this indicator then m's middle
step is here with this triangle
indicator and m's last step is here with
this cross out indicator here. Solid
line
you see the crossed out the solid line
here crossed out is really here going
down and this is more or less here the
worst performance.
What it mean? When more information is
available, you have longer conversation,
more complexity, more data stream,
everything has to be compressed into a
fixed single matrix.
You can't compress it. You only can
compress it to a certain level and then
it's just overflowing. And then the
performance drops sharply.
So after several hundred words for a
really tiny little model recall of
first, the middle and the final facts
become low in the performance or maybe
even unstable. If you continue with
this, what is also interesting, we have
these temporal decay that we expect. Now
as successful updates accumulate more
and more, the earlier memories of course
are overwritten or decay. The middle
memories start really to fluctuate as
the author shows in this paper. And even
the recent memories can become unstable
if we really open a floodgate and we
flood here our fixed size matrix here
with incredible amount of new data. I
mean this was to be expected honestly
because look at this the effect is now
remember we mix here the classical self
attention with the memory attention. So
this will now have effect on the overall
performance of the architecture. So this
means even or once the irrelevant
information is stored the overall
performer can decline because the
mixture of the attention mechanism in
this new transform architecture means
that the native memory that is simply
now overflowing can damage now the
ordinary reasoning process of the
classical self attention process.
So this means the native memory can also
have a negative effect. And look here at
the gap compared to a cuban 3.54b.
Now matis is destroying performance
because its memory mechanism is
overflowing. So we have to choose the
right size for this particular matrix
given your particular job complexity in
your particular domain. So if you work
in mathematics or theoretical physics or
finance or whatever in medicine don't
choose the small too the space too small
because otherwise yeah so this means
native memory is not just a passive
storage it has an influence here on the
classical reasoning model. It modifies
the hidden computation at every equipped
layer in the transformer. And this means
if we store some irrelevant information
or if we have some state information
this can corrupt also the instruction
processing and therefore also the
reasoning processes. So careful this has
now an interconnected complexity that
has a massive effect and can reduce as
you see here in this gap here in the
very last column our performance of the
QN 3.54 billion model.
You remember that I told you that the
the authors of this paper use here not
here the full complexity but they go
here with a low rank decomposition for
the ranks of the memory state. Look at
this. They say okay let's go with a full
memory state. Let's go. This is 124
dimensional. This is the rank. And now
we reduce the rank. And as I showed you
in one of my last videos, I have a rank
normally if I do physics here between I
don't know. Yeah, let's go with 64 128.
Now, as it turns out, if you look here
at the scoring, okay, if you start only
with a rank one, yeah, you have no
performance. Then you go to rank four
for the low rank decomposition, lower,
you get better. 16 rank, you improve.
But at rank 64, you have already reached
the plateau.
So this is now interesting because you
see the numerical values here plateau
out. So this means that the encoding
also you have a mathematical space of
124 rank
is encoded only at a rank 64. So we only
use a tiny subspace of the available
space.
And they show this the full memory state
dimension is 1K but a ring 64 SVD
reconstruction preserved above 99.9%
of the full state average performance.
So this is I would say definitely a new
optimization if you understand and
beautiful study by the orus they show
hey wait a minute our encoding our
compactification if we go with here a
low rank adaptation like in Lara we
encode it here too restrictive we don't
use the whole space no because they show
that a useful short-term memory occupies
here a comparatively low dimensional
subspace which is good if you have only
a little bit of data to be learned in
your conversation. [snorts] But which is
bad if you have a real high complexity,
let's say in physics or you have to
calculate something extreme complicated.
If it then also goes with a low
dimensional subspace, you simply lose
here the information.
Behavioral generalization, we talked
about it. You can forget, it can update.
But of course, we have to ask, hey, to
what lay adapt is this true? Is this
just an answer about the system? because
the information is somewhere
but at least it is not hopefully
available for an answer.
So you might say okay but wait a minute
what was wrong with the original
attention. Now the normal self attention
only assesses here tokens that are
currently inside your context window.
Now I have context window here. 250k, 1
million, 2 million tokens. So beautiful.
But we have other bitter effects that
override this. No. And the solution that
we found is hey we build a harness
around our LLM. And this harness can
compensate now by retrieving now a
markdown entry. No. Yeah. But this means
that the harness must recognize that a
particular data record is relevant for
my particular query. Then the harness
must and the harness is outside of our
LMM remember. Then the harness must
decide and make the active decision to
retrieve it then insert it into the
prompt after some reanking and then make
the LLM process the sentence of the
prompt content here again with this
particular information. So this was our
workaround no with this ordinary self
attention where we had no memory element
in the classical transformer.
What misus now adds is it says listen I
give you a second information highway
within your transformer layer. So what
do you have? We have the ordinary
attention mechanism over the classical
text tokens the current token dynamics.
But I give you something in addition. I
give you a memory directly in your
layers and you can have the memory
attention mechanism that will select now
over the history that you have that the
AI learned either the AI learned itself
or the AI learned with the interaction
with a human the history the last two
months we can compress it into a matrix
and this matrix will be here our
knowledge pool from which we can extract
at particular layer depths It's in the
transformer. We don't need rack. We
don't need any API call. We don't need
any other protocols. It is into our core
LLM deep in the layer. We have memory
attention.
It's a beautiful idea. I love this idea.
Finally, we go the next step. But I told
you at the beginning of this video, it
is a prototype. So therefore, we do have
limitation. And let's be clear and again
I receive always these mails but why you
are so anti-AII why you show us the
limitation of current AI systems why do
just say hey this is perfect and this is
gold standard and because we want to
continue to learn we want to continue to
optimize so therefore we have to
understand what is working what is not
working and what is not working we
optimize so here of the limitations
there is a fundamental failure
mechanisms no all historic target key
value association are superposed into
the same fixed memory matrix now with
misus but this means remember the
geometric subspace and autoonality of
subspaces and and for transform and
everything and value and you got it yeah
this means if unrelated memories that
are not stored in this fixed size memory
matrix are not geometrically separable
they will interfere with each other so
if you don't have orthogonal subspaces
or we take care that some subspaces do
not intervene in the reasoning or the
memory process of the attention
mechanism with other subspaces. We get a
solid out of it.
Matis adds here a learned recurrent and
as I told you a fast weight memory state
inside a frozen transformer. So the
historical interactions are compressed
into dense matrix representation during
the ordinary forward pass. We don't have
to do the complete training and are
later access through a second attention
pathway without replaying the original
text and without interference time
gradient descent. It is only a forward
pass and this is what we do naturally in
our transform architecture.
But unlike rack which pro rides you a
lossless external textual database. Now
your external database can be as almost
unlimited in size. As I told you, Matis
relies here on a fixed size memory
matrix structure. We only have limited
space and therefore we have a
compression mechanism. We have a
parametric compression and yeah we have
the compression itself is not lossless
but we have a lossy parametric
compression mechanisms. And the authors
really explicitly show that as the
number of sequential updates increases.
So if the capacity now increases or the
amount of text in a single step grows
over the capacity, matis begins to
override its matrix representation. This
means more or less it forgets here or it
maybe even scramble earlier facts we
have then not a complete coherent logic
but only fragments left in our matrix
representation. So of course choose the
right size of this matrix. No. So this
leaves me here with the last piece of
information I would like to show you
here from this beautiful study. Have a
look at it. You learn so much. It was so
interesting for me to read this. Mis is
a prototype. But Mis is not yet a
replacement for all of the textual
memory that we use with the classical
Google transformer. Now this native
memory has some beautiful future
possibilities and it may absolutely
complement rag where we have databases
that are huge. But let's be clear in the
current implementation it will not
eliminate here our external memory
modules like rag or this methodologies
because in the classical implementation
it is limited to its memory matrix
structure and the feed process of the
structure.
Yeah, there's a technical detail I have
to mention because as I've showed you
here, some of the formulas here in this
preprint, beautiful, the error analysis,
the equation, they're all about a linear
update process of this memory matrix.
Whereas in the final benchmark that they
published and that I showed you here,
they use here a nonlinear update
function. Now, you have to understand
this is a startup, a Chinese startup
company. Of course they not publishing
everything in their latest details in
their latest development steps. So yeah
they have something here that where they
say hey we can go above linear we have a
better optimization. So just be aware
yes of course and I absolutely
understand this here intellectual
property rights from a startup you
cannot give everything away but the
amount of insight they provide is just
beautiful.
Mis really demonstrates here a
meaningful new engineering and learning
paradigm for our transformer
architecture for our LLMs, VLMs, VLAS.
This means for the complete AI system
that we have. So what we have is our
Lauren semantic compression plus a
persistent fast weight state a new
memory attention mechanism and this
mechanism is a gradientfree online
update just in a feed forward pass. I
mean come on it couldn't be simpler more
elegant and more precise.
Do I have some ideas how to further
develop this? Some ideas how we can
improve this? Absolutely. Hey, I mean
three, four or five ideas, but I just
wanted to show you absolutely amazing.
Go and read some papers that are not
maybe mainstream papers that are not on
Twitter or not on Substack, but have a
look at papers that are hidden. They are
absolutely amazing.
What is the strongest contribution of
this matis paper? It is showing that the
memory write and read policies that we
introduced here can be trained as an
internal transformer computation
compatible with the classical
transformer and then executed with a
forward pass alone. So we have an
absolute compatible version how we do
this and this is exactly at the
beginning of the video I showed you in
hugging face you can download it you can
operate it with the classical hugging
face environment. This is it.
Now the other side the most important
unresolved problem of matrix is equally
fundamental.
We have a fixed latent compression that
produces here this interference produces
here the temporal decay and we hope here
that we have here a controllable or
maybe an uncontrollable pollution if
this particular matrix size is too small
and we simply have override a temporal
decay and therefore we have to come up
with a better solution here for a
dynamic allocation of our resources but
more about this in a later video. What I
wanted to show you they also provide as
a future road map here how this memory
foundation malls will evolve. They start
with a level one stateful capability.
Level two self-managing capabilities.
Level three experience selfarning
capability. Level four a persistent
capability with enduring internal Mars.
and level five here. The absolute crown
here, the self evolving capability with
an open-ended capability evolution. So,
this is absolutely a fascinating paper.
I love it. It's a little bit on the
mathematical side, but if you're
familiar with it, you don't have to
follow your every mathematical detail,
every mathematical index. Just try to
understand here the main idea. And I
hope with this video I provided some
start, some help here. If you are if you
want to read this paper now you know
more or less what it is the main ideas
in this paper. So why not try it out
yourself? I hope to see you in my next
video.